Finding Aid for Chapin family (Niles, Mich.) papers, 1879-1937
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Chapin family (Niles, Mich.) papers 1879-1937
Chapin family
1 linear foot and 4 oversize folders
85112 Aa 2
Niles, Michigan business family involved in various business endeavors, including mining; business papers and plans.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the heirs of Charles A. Chapin (donor 6476 ) in 1980.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Henry A. Chapin of Niles, Michigan, and his son Charles A. Chapin of Chicago, Illinois, were owners of the Chapin Mine in Iron Mountain, Michigan, and partial owners of the Indiana and Michigan Electric Company.
This collection includes business papers of the family of Henry Austin Chapin of Niles, Michigan (1813-1898), his son, Charles Augustus Chapin, of Chicago, Illinois, (who died between 1913 and 1915), and the heirs of Charles Augustus Chapin.
The collection includes business papers relating to the family's operations, including leases, reports, and maps of Chapin Mining Company, operators of the Chapin Mine. There are also leases, correspondence and legal papers of Indiana and Michigan Electric Company relating to power dams at Buchanan and Berrien Springs, Michigan. Other portions of the papers include newsletters and related material of the American Manganese Producers Association; and papers relating to the Chapin Memorial (First) Presbyterian Church, Niles, Michigan.
Subjects:
American Manganese Producers Association.; Berrien Springs (Mich.); Buchanan (Mich.); Chapin, Charles A. (Charles Augustus); Chapin, Henry A. (Henry Austin), 1813-1898.; Chopin family.; Chapin Mine (Iron Mountain, Mich.); Electric industries.; First Presbyterian Church (Niles, Mich.); Indiana and Michigan Electric Company.; Iron mines and mining--Michigan--Iron Mountain.; Iron Mountain (Mich.); Manganese.; Menominee Mining Company.; Niles (Mich.); Presbyterian Church--Michigan--Niles.
- American Manganese Producers Association, newsletters and related material
  - 1929, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1930, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1931, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1932 (Box 1)
- Chapin Memorial (First) Presbyterian Church, Niles, Michigan
  - Papers, 1915 (Box 1)
- Chapin Mining Company, papers
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1889 (Box 1)
  - 1895 (Box 1)
  - 1896 (Box 1)
  - 1901 (Box 1)
  - 1915 (Box 1)
  - 1920 (Box 1)
  - 1922 (Box 1)
  - 1924 (Box 1)
  - 1925 (Box 1)
  - 1932 (Box 1)
  - 1934 (Box 1)
  - 1937 (Box 1)
  - Report, by J. R. Finlay, 1921 and Report, by E. G. Kingsford, undated (Box 1)
  - History of Chapin Mine, 1923, typescript of newspaper article (Box 1)
  - Report, by M. C. Lake, 1927 (Box 1)
- Indiana & Michigan Electric Company
  (papers relating to power dams at Berrien Springs and Buchanan, Michigan)
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1891 (Box 1)
  - 1894 (Box 1)
  - 1897 (Box 1)
  - 1899 (Box 1)
  - 1900 (Box 1)
  - 1901 (Box 1)
  - 1902 (Box 1)
  - 1903 (Box 1)
  - 1904 (Box 1)
  - 1905 (Box 1)
  - 1906 (Box 1)
  - 1907 (Box 1)
  - 1909 (Box 1)
  - 1913 (Box 1)
  - 1915 (Box 1)
  - 1919 (Box 1)
  - 1920 (Box 1)
- Menominee Mining Company
  - Papers, 1879 and 1886 (Box 1)
- Chapin, Hamilton, and Ludington Mines, Oliver Mining Company
  - Plans of underground workings
    - 1908-1910 (Folder 1)
      (oversize folder no. 1)
    - 1911-1913, 1920 (Folder 2)
      (oversize folder no. 2)
    - 1922-1924 (Folder 3)
      (oversize folder no. 3)
    - 1925 (Folder 4)
      (oversize folder no. 4)
    - 1931 (with annotations showing 1931 activity) (Folder 4)
  - Longitudinal sections, 1931 (Folder 4)